Felix Uellendall

Data Engineer, Open Source Enthusiast and Apache Airflow Committer









Email: feluelle@pm.me Web: feluelle.github.io

About Me



Hi, my name is Felix Uellendall. I am a young Data Engineer working in a data team for a digital agency in Berlin, Germany. I joined the Apache Software Foundation in September 2019. Since then I am also an Apache Airflow Committer.

Technical Skills

I am most skilled in: Apache Airflow, Python and Unit Testing

I have experience in: Agile Methodologies, Amazon Redshift, AWS, C#, CI/CD, CSS, dbt, Docker, ETL/ELT, Git, great_expectations, HTML, Java, JavaScript, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Python Pandas, REST, Software Design and Software Development

I am familiar with: Express.js, Kubernetes, Node.js and Test Driven Development

Languages

German (Native speaker) and English (Upper-intermediate)

Projects

Apache Airflow

https://github.com/apache/airflow



"Airflow is a platform to programmatically author, schedule and monitor workflows." - Apache Airflow

In search for a solution for the management of data pipelines I stumbled upon the Open-Source project Apache Airflow in January 2018. I really appreciate the simplicity of use, high coverage of use cases and the community behind it. That's why I decided to give something back so I started contributing and am now a committer of this project.

pi-movies

https://github.com/feluelle/pi-movies



Experience

Apache Software Foundation

https://www.apache.org/

Apache Airflow Committer

September 2019 - Present

"The World's Largest Open Source Foundation" - Apache Software Foundation

For Apache Airflow I am..

- · writing project and code documentation
- · writing unit tests in python
- adding new features like Airflow hooks and operators
- reporting bugs via Jira or GitHub Issues
- communicating with the community via email and slack
- · writing Airflow Improvement Proposals in Confluence
- · reviewing GitHub pull requests
- · helping users to join the community
- · testing and voting releases

Digitas Pixelpark GmbH

https://www.digitaspixelpark.com/

Junior Data Engineer

January 2018 - Present

"Germany's most impactful customer experience agency" - Digitas Pixelpark GmbH

- built a data management platform on AWS for our data analysts and scientists to access analytics data efficiently
- added CI/CD to our DMP (data management platform) via GitLab CI/CD which lints, tests, builds documentation and deploys our code to a development or production environment
- building (ETL/ELT) data pipelines with Apache Airflow
- · connecting new data sources (mostly via REST APIs) to our data platform
- · transforming data via SQL or Python Pandas to be analytics-ready
- · designing workflows efficiently by making use of a lot of features of Apache Airflow
- monitoring of our data pipelines

NETRONIC Software GmbH

https://www.netronic.com/

Student Research Assistant

August 2012 - August 2016

"Our mission is to enable every SMB organization to achieve operational agility with visual scheduling." - NETRONIC Software GmbH

- built a .NET Windows Forms application in C#
- learned that code readibility is important through refactoring and mentorship
- · learned the efficient usage of version control systems
- built a web application accessing Microsoft Azure Active Directoy via a REST API to manage users for one of our products
- · built a hybrid mobile application to let our customers monitor their machines status easily

Education

OSZ IMT

https://www.oszimt.de/

Shortened apprenticeship for software development

September 2016 - January 2018

Oberstufenzentrum Informations- und Medizintechnik

During my time of the apprentice I was working for Publicis Pixelpark GmbH. There I built..

- a REST API with the Spring Framework in Java
- a web application with Node.js, Express.js und Handlebars
- a command line application for our data team for automated transfer of social listening data

FH Aachen

https://www.fh-aachen.de/

ICT with specifics in application development [Incomplete]

August 2013 - August 2016

Aachen University of Applied Sciences

I learned about..

- the basics of programming in C++
- · several other programming languages like Assembly, Prolog and Matlab
- · algorithms and data structures
- IT security and forensic
- · databases and web technologies
- · computer systems architectures, operating systems and distributed systems

Bk GuT

https://www.bkgut.de/

IT assistant and advanced technical college entrance qualification

August 2010 - August 2013

Berufskolleg für Gestaltung und Technik

I learned about..

- the basics of programming in C# and Java
- web development with PHP and MySQL

A Little More About Me

I love creating things, solving puzzles, thinking about code and improving challenging problems. Open Source is what I like doing the most. I enjoy working in the community and share my knowledge with each other.

I also fell in love with the nature and the silence being out there. I like hiking, playing the piano and I am fascinated by the universe.

Felix Uellendall - feluelle@pm.me - References on request

Download resume.pdf